Paradise Court, coming right up.
天堂院 上车就走
Madam...
您请
Thank you.
谢谢
Del.
Del
Oi! What are you doing?!
喂 会不会开车啊
-Thank you.  -Enjoy your stay.
-谢谢  -入住愉快
Bye.
再见
Mr and Mrs Appleby, I presume.
我想您二位一定是Appleby夫妇了
That's us.
没错
-Welcome to paradise!  -Oh, very nice.
-欢迎到天堂来  -哦 真好
Thank you.
谢谢你
Good, good, good.
很好 很好 很好
Come, come, follow me.
来 这边 跟我来
Goodnight.
晚安
Oh, yes. Goodnight.
哦 好的 晚安
And, er, thank you.
还有 呃 谢谢你
There you are!
终于出来了
It's a wonder you hear anything with that racket.
开那么大声你还听得见真是神了
Well, don't just stand gawping, fetch my bags in.
得了 别傻站着 把我的包拿进去
And don't give him too much of a tip.
也别给他太多小费
I'm sure he brought us the long way round.
我敢肯定他绕路了
And found every pothole along the way!
而且颠得要命
Clytemnestra's a friend of yours, is she?
这位慈禧太后是你朋友吗
A relative. My stepmother.
亲戚 我的继母
My condolences. Talk about a backseat driver.
为你默哀 她真是个爱指手画脚的人
It was too fast. It was too slow.
这样太快了 这样太慢了
-The cab was too hot.  -Yeah, that sounds about right.
-车里太热了  -对 她就是这个样子
I can take it from here. How much do I, er...?
放在这里我拿就行了 我要付你多少 呃
Let me just check.
让我看一下
With the excess, that'll be...
算上超额的部分 应该是
-..75 of your new English pence.  -Here you go.
-75新便士  -给
Take 80. Think of it as danger money.
80你拿去 就当精神损失费了
Ta very much.
多谢了
-Did you get it all in?  -Just about.
-都拿进来了吗  -差不多了
Just make sure you put it somewhere safe.
一定要找地方放好
-The rest arrives tomorrow.  -The rest?
-剩下的明天到  -还有剩下的
Well, didn't you get my letter?
你没收到我的信吗
I've sold the house and bought a place in Eynsham.
我把房子卖了 在Eynsham买了个新的
Joyce has got herself engaged
Joyce订婚了
to some man she's living in sin with at Witney.
跟她那个在Witney同居的姘头
Oh, she never mentioned.
哦 她没提过
Well, who's to blame for that if you don't keep in touch?
谁让你不跟我们联系呢
Keith Garrett, his name is.
他叫Keith Garrett
Couldn't you stay with them?
你不能跟他们一起住吗
Do you think I'd be here if I could?
如果能我还来这儿干什么
They're abroad until Wednesday.
他们出国了 周三才回来
Unmarried and both in the same room.
没结婚 还住一个屋
Hm! It's not right.
哼 没规矩
But what about a hotel?
那怎么不去住宾馆呢
Well, you'll be all right on the sofa for a couple of nights.
你就在沙发上凑合几个晚上又不会有问题
I mean, I don't like it any more than you do.
我也不情愿来跟你住
-It's only till I take possession.  -When's that?
-房子办好手续就走  -哪天
There is no need to ask in that tone.
没必要用这种口气问吧
I am not one of your interrogation suspects.
我又不是你的犯罪嫌疑人
Monday.
周一
But you don't have to worry about me.
但是你不需要操心我
I don't expect to be looked after.
我也不用你照顾
Ha! You won't even know I'm here.
哈 你甚至都感觉不到我在这
If you could give your statement to my colleague over here.
请我的这位同事给你录一下口供
It looks to be robbery. Wallet's empty.
像是抢劫 钱包空了
Dudley Lunn, according to the Speedy Cabs office.
死者Dudley Lunn 极速出租车提供的信息
42.
42岁
Married. Uniform's notifying his wife now.
已婚 警员正在通知他的妻子
The paperboy came upon the car just after 6:00.
报童6点的时候发现的车子
Doctor.
法医
Do we know how long he's been there?
他在这大概多久了
Rigor well established,
尸僵很严重
which, as well as making my labours more difficult...
让我的工作难上加难
..suggests he's been dead about 12 hours.
他死了大概有12小时了
Are we sure about that, the time of death?
你确定吗 死亡时间
The glass on his watch is cracked and the hands are set to 6:50.
他的手表碎了 指针停在了6:50
Then the watch stopped ticking several hours before Mr Lunn did.
那他的表就比Lunn先生早寿终正寝了几个小时
The body doesn't lie, Morse.
尸体不会说谎 Morse
Myself notwithstanding,
我还是相信
it's the only impartial, reliable witness to any suspicious death.
死者是任何非自然死亡中唯一公正可靠的证人
So, ten-ish last night, then.
那就是昨晚十点多了
Mm, by my reckoning, yes.
嗯 我估计差不多
Single shot to the back of the skull.
从后脑开了一枪
Point-blank range.
近距离射击
Exit wound just above the left eye.
子弹射出口就在左眼上缘
As you can see...
你能看到
..the bullet strikes the windscreen, drops onto the dash.
子弹击中了前挡风玻璃 掉在了仪表盘上
Et voila
瞧
Looks to be a .22, but it has taken quite a battering.
看起来是22口径的 但是严重变形
I'll be able to give you the def gen after the postmortem.
尸检之后才能给你确切信息
Shall we say 2:30?
我们约两点半吧
It's late for you, Doctor.
这比你平时要久啊 医生
Steak and kidney at The Eagle.
要去老鹰酒吧吃牛排和腰子
I wouldn't want to rush that dissection.
我可不想吃得匆匆忙忙
A cabbie's about as easy a mark as it gets.
出租司机有一个很典型的特征
They have to go out with a decent float,
他们出门的时候一定会揣着一大堆零钱
and it'll only get bigger as the shift goes on.
拉过几单客人之后只会越来越多
There was a driver a couple of weeks ago,
几个礼拜之前有个司机
on our old ground, got put in hospital.
在我们的旧辖区 被送进了医院
Pistol-whipped.
被枪托打晕了
From what he could remember, the suspect was bearded, dark-haired.
据他回忆 嫌疑人有胡子 深发色
-Speedy Cabs again?  -No.
-也是极速出租车吗  -不是
A2B Cars out of Cowley.
是从考利出发的A2B出租
It's a long way to drive to kill someone, isn't it?
杀人倒也不用跑这么远吧
Yeah.
是啊
Private, though. No witnesses.
但这里很私密 没有目击者
Well, that's fine, as far as it goes.
到这一步也没什么问题
But if he kills his ride, how's he gonna get back?
但是如果他杀了司机 要怎么回去
Maybe he didn't have to.
或许他不需要回去
Carry on down the lane aways,
沿着小路往下走
there's a place called Paradise Court.
有个地方叫天堂院
Some sort of naturist camp.
是个天体主义者的大本营
For nudists.
裸露癖
That's where the paperboy was for.
报童就是要去那儿的
What have you got there?
你捡到什么了
-A piece of old tissue?  -All right, matey, don't rub it in.
-一片旧布料吗  -别老戳人痛处 老兄
We haven't all got your eye.
又不是人人都有你那么尖的眼睛
I just thought it might've been something, is all.
我只是想可能是个什么 就捡来看看
Best bag it in any case.
以防万一还是装起来
We'll talk to the family and have a word with his work.
我们去跟他的家人和工作单位聊一聊
Do you want to see if anyone heard anything up at that...
你能不能去那个地方问问有没有人
..place?
听见动静
When he didn't come home,
他没回家的时候
I thought maybe he'd had a long fare, you know?
我还在想他是不是去跑长途了
Somebody might want him to take them to Grimsby.
有人可能想打车去Grimsby
Or anywhere you care to think of.
或者其他哪里
I did say that to the constables who came by earlier.
我跟先前来过的警官说过了
I thought they would have written it down in their notebook or somewhere.
我以为他们都记下来了
But they didn't.
但是他们没有
I'm afraid that's our job, Mrs Lunn.
恐怕这是我们的活儿 Lunn夫人
I'm sorry to have to ask, but...
很抱歉但我得问
..all was well at home, was it?
家里没什么矛盾吧
Oh, yes.
哦 没有
Ours was a very happy marriage.
我们婚姻很和谐
Fenella will be heartbroke.
Fenella一定难过死了
She's out playing right now, but...
她现在在外面玩儿呢 但
..she idolises her father.
她很崇拜她的父亲
You will tell Pauline, will you?
你们会通知Pauline吗
Or have I got to do that?
还是得我去说
Who's Pauline?
谁是Pauline
He was married before.
他的前妻
She lives in Headington.
住在Headington
There's a kiddie, a boy.
他们有一个男孩
She'll have to be told.
如果要告诉她
And she won't thank me for it, will she?
她也不会感谢我的 对吧
I think it's probably better coming from you.
我觉得最好是你们去说
Good afternoon, sir.
下午好 先生
Luggage in the car, is it?
您的行李在车上吗
No, it's, er...
没有 呃
First visit? Well, there's no need to be nervous.
第一次来吗 不必紧张
No need at all.
完全不用
Now, I don't think we've any reservation down for today.
我看我们没有今天的预约
But we've plenty of vacancies.
但是还有不少空房
The season hasn't really got going yet.
旺季还没开始呢
I'm a policeman.
我是警察
And I'm a former major with the Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders.
那我还是阿盖尔与萨瑟兰高地步兵团的前少校军官呢
But the naturist world takes us as it finds us, Mr...?
但是天体主义者的世界待我们一视同仁 怎么称呼
Detective Sergeant Strange, Thames Valley.
Strange警长 泰晤士河谷警局
And I'm not here for a frolic in the altogether, Major...?
我不是来这里裸体嗨皮的 少校
Jones.
Jones
Ahem!
咳咳
If I could have everyone's attention for a moment.
抱歉占用大家几分钟
-This is, er...  -Detective Sergeant Strange, Thames Valley.
-这位是 呃  -泰晤士河谷警局的Strange警长
If you wouldn't mind putting something on while I talk to you.
劳驾各位在跟我说话的时候先穿上衣服
Thank you.
谢谢
Now, I must ask if any of you saw or heard anything unusual last night.
我要请问昨晚你们有没有看见或听见什么异常
I did say, Sergeant, with the music from the luau...
要我说 警长 夏威夷风情宴会放着音乐的时候
-Like a gunshot, you mean?  -Perhaps.
-比如说枪声吗  -之类的
-Miss...?  -Appleby.
-小姐您叫  -Appleby
Alison Appleby, Mrs.
Alison Appleby夫人
I thought it was a car backfiring.
我以为是辆车引擎回火了
Barry Appleby.
我叫Barry Appleby.
Baz.
叫我Baz
What time would that have been?
那大概是几点
The guests all turn their watches in upon arrival
客人们到这里时都把手表上交了
as part of the process of getting back to nature.
这是回归自然过程的一部分
That's true, but I heard the church clock chime ten shortly after.
没错 但是没过多久我就听到教堂敲了十点的钟声
Right.
好的
-No need to go to all that trouble, Mrs Lunn.  -It's no trouble.
-不用麻烦了 Lunn太太  -不麻烦
And Pauline, please.
叫我Pauline吧
I only get called Mrs Lunn
只有律师 社工
by solicitors or the Social or up at Mark's school.
或者Mark学校里的人才叫我Lunn太太
Cowley Secondary Modern? I thought I recognised the uniform.
Cowley现代中学 我好像认得这个校服
-My two went there.  -Oh, yeah?
-我的两个孩子也去那上过学  -是吗
-When was that?  -Oh, a long time past.
-什么时候  -好久之前了
The youngest, my boy, is in the Army now out in Ireland.
我的小儿子现在去了爱尔兰当兵
And my daughter, well, she's with the Welfare looking after kids.
我女儿在福利部门照顾孩子
I probably know her.
我也许认得她
Mark's got into trouble once or twice.
Mark惹过一两次麻烦
He's not a bad boy.
他不是坏孩子
He just misses his dad.
只是想爸爸了
God knows what this will do to him.
天知道这会对他产生什么影响
I'm sorry for asking, but, er...
不好意思我问一下
-..you are divorced, I take it?  -Oh, yeah.
-你应该是离婚了吧  -是的
Four years, last February.
之前二月份的时候就满四年了
Ann is the official Mrs Lunn now. I'm...
现在Ann是正式的Lunn太太 我是
Well, I don't know what you'd call it. What would it be?
不知道你们是怎么叫的 该怎么说呢
The dowager Mrs Lunn?
前Lunn太太
-He gambled, did he?  -Gambled?
-他赌博吗  -赌博
If it had four legs, he couldn't throw money after it fast enough.
只要是有四条腿的 他迫不及待追着扔钱
That and... Well, you've met her.
而且 你们见过她了
How did he meet the second Mrs Lunn?
他是怎么遇见第二任Lunn太太的
Oh, didn't she say? She worked in the cab office.
她没说吗 她在出租车公司做文职
On the radio, handing out the jobs.
负责广播 分派任务
It started there.
就是从那里开始的
They usually fizzled out.
她们基本上都不长久
Only, he got her in the family way and, well...
但是他让她怀了孩子 然后
You said, they usually.
你说 她们基本上
With Dudley it was four legs, good, two legs, better.
对于Dudley来说 四条腿的动物好赌 两条腿的人更好玩
I tried to keep it from Mark as best I could,
我尽量不让Mark知道这些事
but children pick up on things, don't they?
但孩子们总是很敏感 对吧
All right, then, see you back at base.
好的 回公司见
45, 45, pick up 52 Festive Avenue
45 45 到52节日大道接人
going to Headington on account.
送去Headington 记账的
A Mr Benn.
Benn先生
No, it's just awful news.
这事儿太可怕了
Awful.
太可怕了
You heard about what happened
你听说了A2B出租车公司
to the driver from A2B Cars, presumably?
那个司机的事了吗
The fellas have been talking about nothing else.
那家伙把这事儿翻来覆去地说
You hope it's just a one-off. But now this?
还希望是一次性的 但现在又出了这事
Puts the fear of God in everyone.
大家全都胆战心惊的
Oh, sorry about this. Got to answer it.
不好意思 这个得接一下
Usually, we've a girl, but it's her afternoon off.
一般都是个姑娘接 但今天她歇班
Speedy Cabs, can I help you?
极速出租车 您有什么需要
Hello?
喂
Oh, yeah, that's my Siwan.
哦 这是我家Siwan
Joan, she'd be in English.
英文名叫Joan
Though most everybody calls her Birdie.
不过别人都叫她Birdie
Fy nghyw bach.
我的小姑娘（威尔士语）
Always singing round the house, she is. Like a cock linnet.
总是在家里唱歌 像只百灵鸟
Beautiful.
很漂亮
-Have you got kids?  -Yeah, two, as it happens.
-你有孩子吗  -对 有两个
Speedy Cabs, how can I help you?
极速出租车 您有什么需要
Erm, yeah. What time would you like that for?
行 您希望是几点呢
Oh, our pleasure.
不客气
Thank you, now.
谢谢
Goodbye.
再见
Did you give him a job to Hovelle Wood last night?
昨晚你给他派了去Hovelle树林的活吗
Paradise Court, perhaps.
也可能是天堂院
That's where it happened, is it?
就是在那里出的事 是吗
Er, no, erm, well, the last dispatch I had for...
呃 没有 我最后一次给
..for Dudley was... Let me see now. It's all in here, see?
Dudley派活 我看看 都记在这上面 你看
Oh, yeah, here it is, look.
对 在这里 你看
5:18 pick up. Summertown to Beaufort.
5点18分接的 从Summertown去Beaufort
Dr Hu.
Hu博士
Oriental studies.
研究东方学的
Old boy, one of our regulars.
老朋友了 是我们的常客
And there was nothing after that?
在那之后没有了吗
Well, if there was, it didn't come from me.
如果有的话 也不是我分派的
Oh, I had a word with the boys.
我跟兄弟们聊过了
A couple of the lads said he was on the rank at Cowley East last night.
有几个人说他昨晚在考利东区趴活
Do you want some tanning butter?
要擦美黑油吗
-No.  -You don't want to burn.
-不用  -别晒伤了
Where did you get to last night?
你昨晚去哪了
I woke up and you weren't there.
我醒的时候你不在
-Call of nature.  -You were ever such a long time.
-人有三急  -你也去了太长时间吧
Yes, well, I couldn't find it.
对 我找不到厕所
Maybe I should've said...
我是不是应该说出来
..that we'd just come by taxi.
我们是坐出租车来的
You don't think it was our driver, do you?
应该不是我们的司机吧 你觉得呢
No, why would it be?
不是 怎么可能
He dropped us off at 7:30.
他七点半把我们送到
You said yourself, you heard the gunshot around 10:00.
你自己也说 10点左右听到枪响
If that's what you did hear.
如果你真的有听到
He's hardly likely to hang around at the top of the lane all that time.
那段时间他不可能一直在路这头闲逛吧
Was it the top of the lane?
是在路这头出的事吗
Oh, I don't know, do I? I'm just guessing.
我不知道啊 我猜的
Anyway, you don't want to get involved.
反正 别被卷进去了
I wish that man would go and clip his privets elsewhere.
我希望那个人去别的地方修枝
He's staring!
他盯着我们看
8:30, 8:45. Something like that is about the last time we saw him.
8：30 8：45 我们最后一次见他大概就是那时候
-Wouldn't you say, Brian?  -Yeah, that's right.
-你说呢 Brian  -对 没错
Dudley was at the, er, top of the rank waiting for a fare.
趴活等客人的队伍里 Dudley排第一个
Did you see who got into the cab?
你看见上车的人是谁了吗
Er, no.
没有
Did either of you have a job out to Hovelle Wood last night?
昨晚你们有人载客去Hovelle树林吗
-Hovelle Wood?  -Mm-hm.
-Hovelle树林  -嗯
-No, sir, no.  -All right, fellas?
-没有 警官  -怎么样 兄弟们
-What's all this?  -The police, Joe.
-这怎么回事  -警察来了 Joe
-It's about Dudley.  -Dudley?
-是Dudley的事  -Dudley
-What about him?  -You haven't heard?
-他怎么了  -你没听说吗
Oh, my!
天哪
He's been murdered, Mr...?
他被谋杀了 你是
North. Joe North.
North Joe North
Here, don't I...?
哎 我不是
Yeah, Mr North dropped a fare at my house this morning, sir.
对 今早North先生去我家送了个人 头儿
Detective Sergeant Morse. Detective Chief Inspector Thursday.
我是Morse探长 这位是Thursday总警督
So... what happened?
出什么事了
Not another guy like this fella with A2B
该不会跟A2B公司那个人一样吧
We're keeping an open mind, but it looks that way.
我们还没下定论 但看起来就是这样
Here, Clarry, you're up, look.
哎 Clarry 到你了
Oh! If you'll excuse me, officers.
哦 失陪了 警官们
Certainly, Mr Haynes.
没事 Haynes先生
He was keen on the horses, I understand.
听说他热衷赌马
Oh, yes.
对
He was always touching one of us up
他总是找我们
for a couple of quid to put on the gee-gees.
借个几块钱押注在马上
Right. And he liked women, too, I hear.
嗯 听说他还喜欢女人
Well, crumpet in and out the back of the cab all day.
出租车后座上从早到晚那么多浪蹄子进进出出
Can't blame him, can you?
也不怪他 对吧
Well, if anything else
如果你们想到了什么
should cross your mind, you know where to find us.
就来找我们
I can confirm that the bullet which killed Mr Lunn was a .22.
可以确定杀死Lunn先生的子弹是点22口径
I've passed it to Ballistics for a full analysis.
我把它交给弹道检测部门做全面分析了
Small calibre.
小口径
A woman's gun, perhaps?
可能是女式手枪
-Ruth Ellis fired a .38, of course.  -She did.
-Ruth Ellis用的就是点38手枪  -确实
But it wasn't hers.
但那不是她的枪
You're not gonna want to keep a Smith & Wesson in your handbag
你不可能把大口径手枪和化妆品一起
along with your compact, are you?
装在包包里 对吧
Anything else?
还有别的吗
Nothing to suggest any kind of struggle for the weapon.
没有迹象表明死者曾经抢夺过武器
He very likely had no inkling he was about to die.
他很可能完全不知道自己即将被杀害
The Ostrich Fanciers' Club.
鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部
-Never heard of it.  -No address.
-从没听说过  -没有地址
But there is a telephone number on the back.
不过背面有电话号码
I'll see if we can get a reverse trace.
我去查查会不会有别的线索
What will he have had in his wallet, £10, £15, £20?
他的钱包里本来有多少钱 10镑 15 20
-Would you kill someone for that?  -I've seen people killed for less.
-你会为这点钱杀人吗  -为更少的钱杀人我都见过
What are you saying, that emptying the wallet was a blind?
你什么意思 空钱包只是个障眼法
Well, unless I'm much mistaken, that's not just blood on his collar.
除非是我搞错了 他领子上不止有血
That's lipstick.
还有口红
No. If you could keep Fenella with you
不 如果你可以把Fenella带在身边
and I'll fetch her on the way back.
我就在回去的路上接她
They're sending a car for me to go and do the identifying.
他们派了辆车来接我去辨认
I know, I can't believe it myself.
我知道 我都不敢相信
I don't know what I'm going to do for her tea.
不知道跟她喝茶的事该怎么办
He was something of a womaniser,
他就像个花花公子
according to his mates and the first Mrs Lunn.
根据他的同事还有第一任Lunn太太所说
Indeed.
这样啊
Morse noted a smudge of bright, red lipstick on his collar.
Morse在他的衣领上发现了一块亮红色的口红污迹
Another woman, then?
有另一个女人
A jealous husband, perhaps?
也许是个嫉妒的丈夫
Or wife, sir.
或者妻子 长官
Or wife.
或者妻子
'We've 20,000 people on the site.
我们现场有两万人
-'Without a name, I can't really help you.'  -Right. Understood.
-没有名字 我真的帮不上忙  -好的 明白
Well, thank you very much. Sorry to have troubled you.
非常感谢 抱歉打扰了
I've conducted some odd interviews in my time, matey.
询问的时候奇怪的事情我也见过一些 兄弟
But stone me, this morning's go takes the Garibaldi.
但今早这次 真是震惊他妈给震惊开门 震惊到家了
-What's this?  -Paradise Court.
-什么事  -天堂院
The nudie place.
那个天体营
A couple there think they'd heard a gunshot. A Mr and Mrs Appleby.
那里有对夫妻觉得听到了一声枪响 Appleby夫妇
Only, they took it to be a car backfiring just before 10:00.
10点前听到的 不过他们以为那是汽车回火声
Lunn picks his fare up outside the station between 8:45 and 9:00,
8点45到9点之间 Lunn在车站外接乘客
gets to the Hovelle Wood area between 9:45, 10:00.
9点45到10点之间 到达Hovelle树林
That works, more or less.
时间线算是对得上吧
Must've been someone who knows Paradise Court, then.
那肯定是个知道天堂院的人
Get anywhere with The Ostrich Fanciers' Club?
鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部那边有进展吗
Ah, no. There's nothing on record in Oxford. Nothing in the phonebook.
没有 牛津没有任何记录 黄页里也找不到
And the number just gets you the BLMC switchboard.
打这个号码会直接接通利兰汽车公司的总机
But without a name...
但我们不知道名字
-Just going out.  -You just got in.
-我出去走走  -你才刚回来
What about tea?
晚饭怎么办
Well, there's, er...
呃 这有
There's cheese in the fridge and bread in the bin.
冰箱里有奶酪 柜子里有面包
I take it I have to see for myself, then.
那看来我得亲自去找了
Well, you found your way to the drinks cabinet all right.
嗯 你都已经找到酒柜了
I can't imagine the pantry will long prove terra incognita.
食品柜不会那么难找吧
Oh, yes, always the Latin!
噢 得了 又拽拉丁语
Must come in very handy consorting with the criminal classes.
跟犯罪分子打交道定能派上用场
I expect this is one of yours, is it?
我猜这也是你们的案子吧
Taxi drivers murdered in nudist camps.
出租车司机在天体营被谋杀
People running around with no clothes on.
人们一丝不挂地跑来跑去
Urgh!
呕
It's squalid.
真恶心
And you grubbing around in it by way of a living.
你却在那里工作 忙东忙西
I can't imagine what your dad would say.
真不知道你爸会怎么说
Well, not much, if he was running true to form.
按他的一贯风格 应该不会说什么
Still, being the son of a cabbie may have its practical use, for once.
不过 身为的哥的儿子 我的身份这次或许能派上用场
A cabbie?!
的哥
Your father was a private hire chauffeur.
你父亲是私人贵宾车司机
He drove the Aga Khan!
他为阿迦汗开过车
Once.
就一次
He was a taxi driver.
他是出租车司机
Got to drag us down, haven't you?
非得要拉低我们的格调是吧
Belittle him.
贬低他
Make him look small.
让他显得渺小
I can't imagine your father and this dead man have a thing in common.
我想不到你父亲和这个死者有任何共同点
Well, there's the horses. Our dead man liked to gamble.
嗯 赌马 我们的死者也喜欢赌马
Well, there's nothing wrong with that.
这没什么问题
A lot of men like a flutter.
很多男人觉得小赌怡情
Oh, and he left his wife and child for another woman that he'd, erm...
噢 他还抛妻弃子 去找别的女人 呃
What's the polite phrase?
说得好听点叫什么
..put in the family way.
育子
So, there's that, I suppose.
我觉得这就是共同点
Don't wait up.
晚上别等我
You haven't seen my husband, have you, Major?
你见过我丈夫吗 少校
I appear to have lost him.
我好像找不到他了
He asked me to call him a cab.
他让我帮他叫辆出租车
About an hour ago.
大概1小时前
Did he say when he'd be back?
他有说什么时候回来吗
I'm afraid not, Mrs Appleby.
没有 Appleby夫人
-Thank you.  -You're welcome.
-谢谢  -不用谢
The body of Christ.
我主圣体
Amen.
阿门
The body of Christ.
我主圣体
Amen.
阿门
The body of Christ.
我主圣体
Amen.
阿门
Whoa! Whoa...
噢 哇
It's Mark, isn't it?
你是Mark吧
Mark Lunn.
Mark Lunn
I'm Detective Sergeant Morse.
我是Morse探长
I'm investigating what happened to your father.
我在调查你父亲的案子
-You're lying.  -No, I'm not. Let me...
-你骗人  -不 我没有 我给
Let me show you my warrant card.
给你看我的警察证
Every police officer has to have a warrant card,
每个警察都有警察证
to prove he is who he says he is. Look.
用来证明自己的身份 看
Take a look.
看吧
What are you doing here?
你在这干嘛
They come back to the scene of the crime.
他们会回犯罪现场
-Murderers. I've read about it.  -Yeah.
-谋杀犯 我看过  -嗯
-Where did you get the gun?  -My dad gave it to me.
-枪是哪儿来的  -我爸爸给的
He gave it to me for rabbits.
他给我猎兔用的
My dad gave me a gun once.
我爸曾经送我一把枪
For my birthday.
当生日礼物
That was for rabbits, too.
也是用来猎兔的
Can I take a look?
我能看看吗
Swap?
交换
Hey!
嘿
You're too young to be in possession of a firearm.
你太小了 不能持枪
And it's not for you to find out who killed your father.
你也不该来找杀害你父亲的凶手
No matter how much you might want to.
不管你多想亲自出马
I'm staking out the crime scene, in case he comes back.
我要盯着犯罪现场 以防他回来
No, you're going home. And I'm taking you.
不 你回家去 我送你
I know you want to help, but this isn't the way.
我知道你想帮忙 但这样不是办法
Jump in the car.
上车
She won't be a minute, if you want to come up.
她马上就好 你要上来吗
No, no, you're all right, I'll, er...
不用了 谢谢 我 呃
I'll wait here.
我就在这等
Is it, erm...?
漂亮吗
Yeah.
嗯
Oh, yeah.
噢 当然
-I'd forgot to say about gloves.  -I asked someone who'd been to one.
-我忘了说要戴手套了  -我问了去过的人
-I didn't want to let the side down.  -You couldn't.
-我不想让大家失望  -不会的
Should we...?
要出发吗
Yeah, yeah, of course.
啊 对 走吧
I got you these.
我给你带了花
Thank you.
谢谢
Shall we...?
走吧
-Let me get you the door.  -Thanks.
-我来为你开门  -多谢
Mind your dress.
当心裙子
Don't you look a picture.
你真是美如画
-Shall we, squire?  -Let's.
-走吗 先生  -走吧
I thought, if I got a better report, he might come back.
我以为 要是我成绩变好 他就会回来
How do you mean?
什么意思
From school.
学校
I got a bad report and he was cross about it.
寄来了我的成绩单 很差 他很生气
Then he went and lived with his new family.
然后他就走了 去和他的新家人一起住
But...
但
Well, that was just a coincidence.
那只是个巧合
That wasn't your fault.
不是你的错
Your mum and dad getting divorced
你爸妈离婚
had nothing to do with anything that you said or did,
和你的所作所为或不作不为
or didn't do or say. Do you understand?
没有任何关系 明白吗
He was a good dad.
他是个好爸爸
Yeah, I'm sure. I'm sure.
嗯 确实 确实
He'd let me help at the garage sometimes
他开出租车的时候
-when he was working on the cab.  -Yeah?
-有时会让我去修车厂帮忙  -是吗
Did you enjoy that?
你喜欢吗
Can I have my gun back?
我能拿回我的枪吗
No.
不行
Er, you can't. It's...
呃 不行 这是
It's illegal, I'm afraid.
这是违法的
You're just as likely to hurt yourself with it as someone else.
你和其他人一样 很可能伤到自己
So, I'll keep hold of it until you're old enough, all right?
所以 我替你代为保管 直到你长大 好吗
Now, go on. Go in and give your mum a hug.
好了 去吧 进去给你妈妈一个拥抱
Tell her you love her.
告诉她你爱她
Goodnight.
再见
Can I see?
我能看看吗
Oh, certainly.
当然可以
It's amazing.
太美了
You're very welcome to it.
你可以拿走它
You mean it, I could keep it?
你是说 我能留下它吗
By all means, if you'd like it.
要是你喜欢 请务必收下
Could you sign it?
你能签个名吗
Oh, now...
行
-How's that?  -R Bright.
-怎么样  -R Bright
What does the R stand for?
R是什么的缩写
Reginald.
Reginald
I'm Lynn.
我是Lynn
-Lynn Parry.  -Miss Parry, how do you do?
-Lynn Parry  -Parry小姐 你好啊
Lynn.
叫Lynn就好
Mr and Mrs Denby.
Denby夫妇
Mr and Mrs Cameron.
Cameron夫妇
Brother Strange and Miss Joan Thursday.
Strange修士和Joan Thursday小姐
-Worshipful Master.  -Brother Strange.
-尊主你好  -Strange修士你好
-What a beautiful dress.  -Oh, you're very kind.
-礼服真美  -噢 你嘴真甜
Not at all, it's really gorgeous.
不 它真的很美
Thank you.
谢谢
I hope you have a lovely evening.
祝你们今晚愉快
We will, I'm sure.
一定会的
Mr and Mrs Stubbings.
Stubbings先生和夫人
And the winner of two tickets
获得皇家阿尔伯特音乐厅
to see The Carpenters at the Royal Albert Hall is...
卡朋特乐队演唱会的两张门票的是
..Mr James Strange and Miss Joan Thursday!
James Strange先生和Joan Thursday小姐
Cheers!
干杯
-Some of us are trying to sleep!  -Oh, good evening.
-我们要睡觉了  -噢 晚上好
Never mind good evening. What do you want?
别晚上好了 你想干嘛
-I'm looking for Miss Thursday.  -Well, she's out.
-我找Thursday小姐  -她出门了
Out?
出门
Some bloke in an evening suit and a private car.
跟一个穿晚礼服 坐私家车的家伙
Oh...
噢
-Was there a message?  -No.
-要留言吗  -不用
No, no message.
不用留言
# Earth angel, Earth angel
# 凡间天使 凡间天使
# Will you be mine?
# 你会属于我吗
# My darling, dear
# 我亲爱的 亲爱的
# Love you all the time...
# 爱你到永远
-Here we go...  -Thank you.
-给  -谢谢
-All right?  -So far, so good.
-还好吗  -目前还行
I didn't say anything that was...? Mm.
我是不是说错话了
No. No, not at all. You were brilliant.
不 完全没有 你棒极了
So...
所以
..what's this all about, then, Jim?
Jim 这活动是干嘛的
Well, it's kind of expected, isn't it, in my line?
呃 这不是像我们这样的人应该做的嘛
Not many of us went to the right kind of school, so...
我们之中很多人都没去过正经学校
-..this is the next best thing.  -Old boy network.
-但这样也不错  -校友关系网嘛
If you like.
这么说也可以
There's no harm in it. The way people go on,
这事也没害处 这里人做事的方式
you'd think it's all black magic and sacrificing virgins.
会觉得是在施展什么黑魔法 还要献祭处女
But somewhere in amongst all that,
但不知道怎么回事
somehow, we manage to do a lot of good work for charity.
我们还是成功地为慈善事业贡献了不少
Did you want to, er...?
呃 你想不想
Why not?
为什么不呢
Thank you.
谢谢你
Allow me.
我来吧
# ..happiness
# 幸福
# Earth angel, Earth angel
# 地球天使 地球天使
# Please, be mine
# 请成为我的
# My darling, dear
# 我亲爱的 亲爱的
# Love you for all time
# 爱你永不变
# I'm just a fool
# 我只是个傻瓜
# A fool in love
# 爱你的
# With you.
# 傻瓜
Hey!
嘿
Hey, what the hell do you think you're doing?!
嘿 你他妈在想什么
I could've killed you!
我也许会撞死你
What...? Officer...
什么 警官
-..are you OK?  -I'm sorry.
-你还好吗  -抱歉
Come on, sir. Come on, let me help you.
长官 起来吧 站起来 我来帮您
Who's this?
你是谁呀
-Are you OK?  -Yeah, I just tripped and...
-您没事吧  -没事 我就是有点儿没站稳
..and missed my footing a little bit.
突然绊了一跤
That could have happened to anyone. Which way are you going?
谁都可能会这样 您往哪个方向走啊
Erm, this way.
呃 这边
Look, let Clarry take you home safe, sir.
长官 让我开车把您安全送到家吧
Come on, the car's there, sir. Come, come.
这边 车在这边 长官 过来吧 来吧
You scared the life out of me, man.
你真是要把我魂吓出来了
Thank you.
谢谢
Well, listen, thanks for helping me out tonight.
谢谢你今晚帮我
You're welcome.
不客气
Right, night, then.
那就晚安了
Night.
晚安
Blimey.
老天爷呀
I won't wash my face for a week now.
我之后一周都不会洗脸了
What was that for?
你为什么笑呀
A lovely evening.
今晚过得很愉快
Go on, in you go.
进去吧 快进去
Oh, listen, don't feel like
噢 对了 不用觉得
you've got to come to The Carpenters if it's not your...
你必须得去卡彭特乐队演唱会 如果你不感兴趣
Excuse me, we won, didn't we?
什么呀 我们赢了 不是吗
-Yeah, but...  -A night out in London?
-是 但是  -伦敦一夜游
I'm not gonna turn that down.
我可不会拒绝这个
She does have a lovely voice.
她唱歌是很好听的
Yeah, she does.
是的 确实
Right, then, goodnight.
好了 那就 晚安
Goodnight.
晚安
Phwoar!
哇哦
Nice bit of crumpet.
这马子真不错
She's not crumpet.
她不是马子
She's a smart, bright, independent, young woman.
她是位聪颖 开朗 独立的年轻女性
You'll remember it if you're looking for a tip next time.
下次想拿到小费的话可要记住了
Whatever you say, squire.
听你的 骑士
Are you all right, now?
你现在感觉还行嘛
Yep.
还行
Thanks for the lift.
谢谢你载我回家
Oh, it's all right, I've got them.
噢 没事了 我找到了
Father Francis Mahoney.
Francis Mahoney神父
56.
56岁
-Who found him?  -His housekeeper.
-谁发现的  -他的管家
A Mrs Walsh.
Walsh夫人
She brought him a cup of tea to his room at the rectory,
她去他教区长住宅的卧室送茶
only to find his bed hadn't been slept in.
发现他的床没有睡过的痕迹
So, she came in here to look for him.
所以她来这边找他了
She doesn't live in, then?
她是不和神父住一起吗
Goes home of an evening after he's had his tea.
她在神父晚上喝完茶后离开
Then comes in first thing to see to his breakfast.
然后一早过来准备早餐
Looks to be another robbery, in any event.
不管怎么说 看起来又是一起抢劫案
Wallet's open and empty on the floor of the confessional.
钱包丢在忏悔室的地上 被打开了 里面空空如也
Anything, Doctor?
医生 有什么发现吗
I'm afraid Father Mahoney
恐怕Mahoney神父
got rather more of an earful than he was expecting.
听到的忏悔比他想的要多不少
Shot through the screen.
子弹从屏风射过来
Body temperature and rigour suggests he joined the choir invisible
从尸体温度和僵硬程度来判断 他大概14到16小时前就
about 14 to 16 hours ago.
离世了
That makes it sometime after last night's seven o'clock mass.
那就是晚上七点弥撒之后发生的啊
Doesn't confession happen before mass,
忏悔不应该在弥撒前吗
unless it's prearranged with the priest?
除非是牧师提前安排好的
There's no exit wound this time, so calibre will have to wait on the PM.
这次不是贯穿伤 所以子弹口径结果要到下午才能出来
Might we remove the body?
我们能把尸体移走吧
Of course, Doctor. By any means.
好的 法医 完全没问题
Very well, then. Shall we say two o'clock?
很好 那我们约个两点吧
What would a taxi driver and a priest have in common
出租车司机和牧师会有什么共同点
that would be of interest to the same killer?
会让同一个凶手感兴趣
Until we have forensics on the bullet, we don't know they were.
弹道鉴定结果出来前 不能判定是同一凶手所为
What, two shootings in two days by two different killers?
什么 两天内两起不同凶手犯下的枪击案
That hardly seems likely, does it?
这好像不太可能吧
I went back to Cowley East to talk to the station staff last night.
我昨晚又去了考利东区和店员们聊了聊
The waitress at the cafe
咖啡店的服务生说
said a cleric had been in the night that Lunn was killed.
Lunn被杀的那晚有个牧师在那里
Hanging about over his coffee.
边喝咖啡边闲逛
-Mahoney?  -One dog collar's much like another.
-是Mahoney吗  -牧师穿得一样 看上去都差不多
We'll see if there's any photos of him up at the rectory
我们去教区长房子里看看有没有他的照片
-and you can run it past her.  -Right.
-你可以带给她去辨认一下  -好
She also said there was a young woman.
她还说那时候还有个年轻女人
Blonde. Twenties. Kept watching the cab rank.
金发 二十多岁 一直在看出租车队
Get going with door to door.
你去附近挨家挨户问一下
-We'll brace the housekeeper.  -Sir.
-我们去拜访一下管家  -是 长官
What happened to you this morning?
你今天早上怎么回事
Oh, I'm sorry, I, er... I missed the alarm.
噢 抱歉 呃 我 我没听见闹钟
That shirt looks like you've slept in it.
这衬衫皱得像你昨晚穿着它睡的一样
I've got my stepmother staying with me
我继母搬过来和我住了
until she moves into a place in Eynsham.
一直到她在Eynsham的房子可以入住
I'm on the sofa. It's not ideal.
我在沙发上睡 睡不好
Still no excuse for a grubby shirt.
那也不是衬衫脏兮兮的借口
Slovenly dress leads to a slovenly mind.
穿得邋遢 思想就邋遢
If more connects these cases than robbery,
如果这两起案子不仅仅是抢劫的话
then I'll need you to earn your keep.
我希望你干的活对得起你挣的钱
Well, I wasn't completely idle last night.
我昨晚并不是什么都没干
I went back to where Lunn was shot.
我又去了一趟Lunn的案发现场
I almost went the same way myself.
差点就落得和Lunn一样的下场了
His son was lying in wait in case the killer returned to the scene.
他儿子就在那儿等着 等着凶手重回案发现场
-You mean, he was armed?  -Yeah, a .22 pistol.
-你是说 那小孩有武器  -是的 0.22口径的手枪
Same as did for his old man.
和杀了他爸爸口径一样的枪
Don't worry, I took it off him, and then drove him home.
别担心 我从他那拿走了 把他送回家了
But while I was there, I found part of a metal canister
而且我在那里的时候 我还发现了一个金属小罐
on the verge by where the taxi was parked.
就在出租车停着的地方边上
-What sort of canister?  -I couldn't say.
-什么样的罐子  -说不好
I'd intended to take it to this naturist camp,
我本来想带着它去天体营
but with the boy on board...
但车上还有个小男孩
Pass it to Forensics for prints,
把它交给鉴证科 查查指纹
along with the pistol for comparison testing.
还有手枪 也去做对比测试
-Do you want to come down?  -No, you're all right.
-麻烦你下来一下吧  -不了吧
Mrs Walsh said it would be all right to carry on.
Walsh夫人说可以继续干
Well, I'm saying it's not.
我说可不行
So, if you don't get down here and give your details to my sergeant,
所以 你要是不从梯子上下来 不把详细情况跟我的警长讲清楚
you'll have my foot up your arse!
我可要给你点颜色看看
Come on, Pops, don't be uptight. I've got a rota.
警长们 别这样 别这么暴躁嘛 我有一堆活要干呢
If I don't do them now, it'll put me all out.
如果我现在不干的话 不会有好果子吃的
I'll put you all out if you don't get down that ladder!
你不从梯子上下来的话 我现在就不会给你好果子吃
All right, all right, keep your hair on.
好吧好吧 别激动
Blimey, what's the matter with him? Ain't he getting any?
妈呀 他怎么回事 怎么脾气这么大
-Name, address and date of birth, please.  -Lee Timothy.
-请报一下姓名 住址 出生年月  -Lee Timothy
3 The Sidings, Jericho.
住在Jericho The Sidings 3号
12th October, 1950.
1950年10月12日生
When was the last time you saw Father Mahoney?
你最后一次见Mahoney神父是什么时候
Six weeks. The last time I did his windows.
六周前 上次我替他擦窗户的时候
Did he ever mention any trouble he was having?
他有提到过他遇上了什么麻烦吗
Any difficulties with his parishioners?
和他的教区居民有什么过节吗
To his window cleaner?
对他的窗户清理工讲吗
No.
没有
Right.
行吧
Funny enough...
但有件事很有意思啊
..I did hear him have a bit of a ding-dong last I was here.
上次我在这儿的时候确实听到他和别人发生点口角
I was aloft doing the window.
我那时在擦窗户
He was having a right old go at someone in the front bedroom.
他在前边的卧室冲某个人发火
The top bay.
顶楼凸出的那个房间
Did you hear what he was saying, or see who he was talking to?
你听见他讲什么了吗 或是看见他在和谁说话吗
No, not who was with him, but...
没有 没看到是谁 但是
..I saw a trilby on the hall table.
我看到大厅桌子上有顶毡帽
Little orange feather in the band. Too racy for the Father.
带子上有几根橙色羽毛 神父可不戴这么活泼的
-What time was this?  -Early doors.
-那是什么时间  -早上挺早的
Right, I think that will be all for now, Mr Timothy, thank you.
好 现在应该没什么问题了 Timothy先生 谢谢你
If we need anything else, we'll be in touch.
如果我们还需要什么的话 会联系你的
His ministry had taken him all over.
他做牧师的时候浪迹四方
He'd been a padre in the war, I think.
我记得 他好像去当过战时牧师
And a prison chaplain, too.
还当过监狱牧师
Did he have any family that you know of?
你知道他有什么家人吗
He had a half-brother come by from time to time.
他有个继兄会时不时过来
Donal.
叫Donal
But things weren't all that good between them.
但他们关系并不太好
No?
关系不好
How's that?
为什么
He turned up every few months...
他隔几个月就会来一次
..like the proverbial bad penny.
像狗皮膏药一样甩都甩不掉
After money from the Father.
找神父要钱
I told him I thought he was taking advantage.
我跟他说过 我觉得他就是赖上他了
The Father said...
神父说
.."Am I not my brother's keeper, Roisin?"
我不就是我弟弟的监护人吗 Roisin
"Am I not my brother's keeper?"
我不就是我弟弟的监护人吗
-Afternoon, Mrs Appleby.  -Afternoon.
-下午好 Appleby太太  -下午好
Baz!
Baz
Where the hell have you been?
你死哪去了
-I've been going out of my mind.  -It's not a big deal.
-我都快急疯了  -没什么大事
I just had to get away.
我只是得离开一下
-From me?  -No, from here.
-离开我吗  -不是 是离开这里
-It was just for an hour or two.  -Baz, you've been gone all night.
-就一两个小时  -Baz 你出去了一整晚
Where did you go?
你去哪了
A pub in town.
镇上的一家酒吧
An old haunt from when I was an undergrad.
我读大学的时候常去
I had too much to drink and passed out on Christchurch Meadow.
我喝多了 在基督教堂的草坪上醉倒了
But I'm back now.
但我这不是回来了吗
-I'll try and make a go of it.  -You don't have to.
-我会再努力试试看的  -不必勉强
-You can just go.  -No, I'd like to.
-想走就走吧  -不 我愿意
Really.
真的
I'll get over my hang-ups and...
我会克服自己的抵触心理 再说了
..we've paid for the week.
我们付了一周的钱呢
Let's just try and enjoy it.
不如试着好好享受吧
Yes?
好吗
-Anything from lippy?  -No, nothing much.
-小贫嘴那儿有什么收获吗  -没有 没什么重大突破
Oh, other than he overheard Mahoney arguing with someone in his bedroom
哦 除了他上次来的时候无意中听见
the last time he was here.
Mahoney在卧室里跟人争吵
-Man or woman?  -He couldn't say.
-男的女的  -他说不准
Though he did see a trilby through the window with an orange feather.
不过他透过窗户看到了一顶带橘色羽毛的软毡帽
Not Mahoney's. So, presumably, a man.
那不是Mahoney的 所以 应该是个男的
Could be his half-brother Donal.
可能是他同父异母的弟弟 Donal
Well, there's a...
这儿倒是写了个
There's a "call D" in his diary.
他日程簿里写了个 打电话给D
And his last appointment is confession.
而且他最后一场预约确实是做忏悔
8:00pm. Ringed and underlined.
晚八点 圈起来还打了横线
Kept by his killer, presumably.
来赴约的应该就是杀他的凶手
Mm.
嗯
The fruit of my labour.
我的劳动成果
22, the same calibre as did for Mr Lunn.
0.22英寸 跟杀死Lunn先生的子弹口径相同
By your leave, I'll pass it to Forensic Ballistics for comparison.
你们不介意的话 我就把它送去法医弹道专家那做比对了
See if we have a match.
看看是否一致
Well, I can't imagine we've too many robbers going round Oxford
我想我们应该没那么多
knocking people off with a .22 pistol.
带着把22口径手枪在牛津到处伤人的抢劫犯
Three feathers.
三根羽毛
That was on Lunn's membership card, wasn't it?
Lunn的会员卡上也有这个吧
Mm, The Fanciers' Club.
嗯 鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部
"From the boys on D wing, Wandsworth."
旺兹沃斯监狱D翼楼的弟兄们赠
His housekeeper said he was a prison chaplain.
他的管家说他以前做过监狱神父
It's a funny robbery that leaves a pocket watch.
抢劫犯放着怀表不要 挺奇怪的
And it's smashed again.
这只也摔坏了
Two broken timepieces?
两块表都坏了
The killer's motif, perhaps?
会不会是凶手杀人的固定模式
Do you still think it was just a robbery?
你还觉得这只是一起抢劫案吗
3:50...
三点五十
So, what's he after?
那他这么做图什么呢
Trying to fix a false time to give himself an alibi, maybe?
会不会是想让我们搞错死亡时间 好让他有不在场证明
Well, if that's his purpose, it's pretty redundant.
如果是为了这个目的 多此一举啊
We know from Doctor DeBryn and from his appointment book
DeBryn医生还有他的预约登记簿都能告诉我们
that Father Mahoney was shot at 8:00.
Mahoney神父是在八点遭遇枪击
Well, whatever it means, I'd better get back and brief Mr Bright.
不论这意味着什么 我还是先回去汇报给Bright先生吧
Two deaths in as many days isn't gonna go down well at Division.
两天死俩 分局那边的人听了肯定笑不出来
You can bank on it.
你就等着瞧吧
I'll get back to the rectory, see if there's anything that this fits.
我回神父住所看看有没有适合佩戴这只怀表的衣服
There was a wardrobe that I couldn't get into.
那儿有个衣柜我打不开
Just to make sure nothing's been overlooked.
我去确认一下有没有遗漏什么
A taxi driver, and now a priest.
先是出租车司机 现在又死了个神父
Anything to connect them?
他们之间有关联吗
We've no reason to believe the dead men were known to each other, sir.
没有证据表明两名死者互相认识 长官
Well, whoever's behind it, you need to find them, Thursday, and fast.
不论幕后凶手是谁 你得抓住他们 Thursday 要快
I've already had Division on.
我已经给分局安排下去了
If this is some lunatic murdering strangers at random for money...
如果这是个随机挑陌生人谋财害命的疯子
..he's got 130,000 potential victims to choose from,
他有13万名潜在受害者可以随便挑
and we've no way of knowing who's going to be next.
我们根本无法预知谁会是下一个
Can't you wear a bell around your neck?
你不能在脖子上挂个铃铛吗
Sorry. I've always been light of foot.
抱歉 我脚步一向很轻
What are you doing skulking in there?
你躲里面干嘛呢
-Looking for absolution?  -It's too late for me.
-寻求宽恕吗  -对我来说太迟了
I'm past saving.
我已经无可救药了
It's never too late for the Almighty.
在上帝眼中 什么时候都不算晚
"Though your sins be as scarlet..."
你们的罪虽像硃红
Did you know him? What was he like?
你认识他吗 他是个什么样的人
Whisky priest.
他没表面上那么庄严
They get that look sometimes, clergy. That...
他们神职人员有时会露出那种神情 那种
..over-the-shoulder hunted cast to the eye,
一边逃命一边回头看的惊恐眼神
as if they'll be discovered in their doubt.
像是怕被人发现他们信仰不够坚定一样
You mean, he lost his faith?
你是说 他迷失了信仰
Well, there's a lot of it about.
这在这一带挺常见的
Have you ever heard of The Ostrich Fanciers' Club?
你听说过鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部吗
No, that's new to me.
没有 第一次听说
-Where is it?  -I don't know.
-在哪  -不知道
-I'm not even sure what kind of club it is.  -I can ask around.
-我都不清楚它到底是个什么俱乐部  -我可以打听打听
Aye-aye, what's this, then?
嚯 这儿干嘛呢
A magic lantern show?
看幻灯片呢
In a manner of speaking.
算是吧
Oh! Blimey!
哦 天哪
Morse found a bunch of them in a wardrobe up at the rectory.
Morse在神父住所的一个衣柜里找到了一堆这玩意儿
All right, Morse.
行了 Morse
We get the general idea.
我们大概清楚怎么回事了
Pornography?
色情片
That's not Oxford business. That's London business.
牛津不兴这个啊 伦敦才有吧
An hour's run up the A40 makes it everybody's business.
开车走A40高速公路就一小时车程 谁都别想好
I've got an old colleague in the Dirty Squad.
我在下流犯罪小队有个老同事
I'll see if he can shed any light.
我可以让他帮忙看看
Well, it wasn't Father Mahoney at the station cafe.
去车站咖啡馆的不是Mahoney神父
I showed his photo to the waitress. She said it was another fella.
我给服务员看了他的照片 她说是别人
Hello, hello, that's, er...
咦 那是
-..a Masonic apron.  -Yeah, we know.
-共济会的围裙  -没错 我们知道
It was with the blue films in the bag.
它和那些黄片一起装在包里
Well, it couldn't have been Father Mahoney's. The Pope stuck a ban
它不可能是Mahoney神父的 教皇约200年前就明令禁止
on Romans joining the Brotherhood nearly 200 years back.
天主教徒加入共济会
His brother Donal, maybe.
可能是他弟弟Donal的
-He sounds like a wrong 'un.  -Sir...
-他听着就不是什么好东西  -长官
These canisters...
这些罐头
A tin can, you say?
你说锡制罐头
Well, you find all sorts in hedgerows.
树篱里什么都有嘛
No, it was half a canister.
不 是半个罐头
It may have contained eight millimetre film stock.
里面可能装过8毫米的胶片
Well, we have a film show once a week for the guests.
我们每周都会为客人们安排一场电影
We've a small library of them, but they're all 16 mil.
我们收藏了一些影片 但都是16毫米的
The couple that heard the shot, Major, Mr and Mrs Appleby,
听见枪响的那对夫妻 少校 Appleby夫妇
-when did they arrive?  -Friday evening.
-他们什么时候到的  -周五晚上
We gave them their flower garlands by way of a welcome.
我们为他们戴上了花环作为欢迎
I asked if they wanted to dine,
我问过他们要不要用餐
but they were very tired and wanted to get straight to bed.
但他们都很疲惫 想直接去睡觉
We didn't see them again till morning.
我们直到早上才再次见到他们
We were going to drive up, but then we thought,
我们本来打算开车来的 但后来我们想着
if we really are going to get back to nature
如果我们真想回归自然
we ought to take the train and get a cab.
我们就该先坐火车 再打个车
And can you describe the driver?
还记得那位司机什么样吗
-The driver?  -Mm-hm.
-司机  -嗯
Oh, yes.
哦 记得
You lied to us.
你对我们撒谎了
Turns out you were the one
原来你才是
who dropped the Applebys at Paradise Court
谋杀当晚
the same night as the murder.
送Appleby夫妇到天堂院的人
I can see I should have mentioned it, but I've had a lot on my mind.
现在想来我确实应该提一下 但我忙昏头了
My wife's been sick, sir.
我妻子病了 警官
-Back and forth to the doctor.  -I'm sorry to hear it.
-反反复复看医生  -我很遗憾
And where were you last night?
你昨晚在哪
Well, now, sir, you know where I was.
我说 警官 您知道我在哪啊
I had a little accident with the officer.
我跟这位警官出了点小事故
But I made sure he was all right and took him home.
但我确认了他没事 还送他回了家
Before that.
在那之前呢
Oh...
哦
I had fares all over.
到处接送乘客啊
Anything take you near St Agnes?
有去St Agnes附近的单子吗
No, sir, I don't believe it did.
没有 警官 我不记得到过那边
And was everything all right between you and Mr Lunn?
你和Lunn先生关系还好吗
-Me and Dudley?  -Yeah.
-我和Dudley  -对
Yeah, sure, we was good friends, you know.
当然好啊 我们可是好哥们儿
-Ask any of the men on the rank.  -No money worries or anything?
-随便找个同行问问  -没有金钱之类的纠纷吗
It's just I found this marker in the back of your cab last night.
只是我昨晚在你车后座上找到了这张借条
It's an IOU for £25 on the back of a Speedy Cabs card
25镑的欠条 写在了极速出租车名片的背面
and signed by Mr Lunn.
上面有Lunn先生的签名
Oh, now, see, sir, that...
哦 这个嘛 警官 那个
That was just a little private matter between us.
那只是我们之间一件小小的私事
Besides, Dudley paid all of that back a long time ago.
况且 Dudley早就还清了
In my experience, Mr Haynes, when a debt is paid,
以我的经验 Haynes先生 欠的钱要是还清了
the marker's returned to the debtor.
借条会还给借款人
Else destroyed.
或者销毁
Also, £25, what's that?
另外 25镑 这是多少
A week's wages or more.
一周的薪水 可能还不止
Well, sir...
我说 警官
..we all puts a little bit by for a rainy day, don't we?
我们都会存点钱以备不时之需的吧
But you can see why we're finding it difficult to believe
但是相信你也清楚 我们很难相信
that you being out at Paradise Court
欠了你钱的受害者被枪杀的那晚
on the same night that a man, who owes you money, is shot dead
你明明去了天堂院
is something that might just slip your mind.
却说自己忘记了这件事
Look...
好吧
Maybe I should've said something.
或许我是该说些什么
But I didn't want to get involved in that kind of trouble.
但我不想卷入这些麻烦之中
Murder trouble, you know.
谋杀案 你懂的
I'm just a taxi driver.
我只是个出租车司机
I mind my business.
我只管接送乘客
Mr and Mrs Maynard?
Maynard先生 太太
-Good afternoon.  -Good afternoon.
-下午好  -下午好
Thank you.
谢谢
Farewell, my dear.
再见 亲爱的
-Have a lovely trip.  -Thank you.
-旅途愉快  -谢谢
-See you in a few days, darling.  -I'll get the door.
-回见 亲爱的  -我来开门
And here's your coat.
外套给你
Thank you.
谢了
-Drive safely.  -Will do.
-注意安全  -放心吧
Right, to the station, then.
好 那就去车站了
Well, if this is what you get up to living here by yourself,
好嘛 如果你一个住在这里就是干这些
no wonder you can't get a decent girl to look at you.
难怪没有正经女孩看得上你
It's evidence.
这是证据
In a murder case.
谋杀案的
There's more to the world than you find in Reveille, Gwen.
坐井观天 曰天小者 非天小也 Gwen
And you'd know all about it, I'm sure.
确实 你什么都懂
Because you went to Oxford.
毕竟你考上了牛津
But you didn't finish it, though, did you?
却没读完 不是吗
For all your books and your poetry...
就为了你那些书啊诗的
..and your snooty music...
还有高雅音乐
-..you failed.  -Yep!
-辍学了  -没错
Yep, I failed.
没错 我辍学了
I should have stayed at home and...
我就应该呆在家里
..drove a taxi, like my father.
开辆出租车 像我爸一样
And then got one of the local girls knocked up.
然后把一个当地女孩的肚子搞大
Then you could look down your nose at me, and all would be well
这样你就可以对我颐指气使 在你的方寸世界里
in your tiny, little world.
一切都是如此完美
You were always a strange one.
你从来就是个怪咖
Close and private.
离群自闭
Filled with your sweaty, little secrets.
满脑子都是见不得人的小秘密
-You were a disappointment to him.  -So you said.
-你真是令他失望  -你说的对
A big disappointment. So you said.
-失望至极  -你说的对
I didn't kill her!
我没有害死她
What?
什么
I didn't give her cancer.
我没有让她得癌症
And you can't blame me all your life.
你不能一辈子都怪在我头上
I've got work to do.
我还有工作要做
Goodnight, Gwen.
晚安 Gwen
We took you in.
是我们收留了你
It's Lunn? You're sure?
那是Lunn 你确定
It's definitely him. He's in two or three of the pictures.
肯定是他 有两三张图里都有他
That's his connection to Father Mahoney.
这是他和Mahoney神父之间的联系
Lunn's a performer in these blue films, which...
Lunn是这些色情片的演员之一 这些片子
There's no need to clam up on my account.
你们不必在我这里有什么忌讳
Oh, I'll get it.
噢 我去接
I was in Blackpool with the ATS for two years during the war.
二战期间 我和ATS一起在Blackpool
And there was this man
就是这个男人
and he kept asking me if he could measure my feet.
他一直问能不能量量我脚的尺寸
I know, it takes all sorts, but...
我知道 这需要很多因缘际会 但
..there we go.
我们走到了今天
You're looking tired.
你看起来很疲惫
It's work.
工作如此
You must look after yourself.
你一定要照顾好自己
We all think a lot of you, you know?
我们都很挂念你 你知道吗
I'm sorry you've had a bad go.
我很抱歉 你有过一些糟糕的经历
-Right.  -Well...
-好了  -那么
Come home safe, Dad.
平安回来 孩子他爸
Morse.
Morse
That was the factory.
那是一个制片基地
He's the Worshipful Master at my lodge.
他是我们共济会会所的会长
Commodore Maynard. Harry Maynard.
Maynard准将 Harry Maynard
I only saw him the night before last at the, er...
我只在前天晚上见过他
..the lodge.
在会所里
Who found him?
谁发现他的
A beat constable.
一个巡警
Anonymous tip-off.
匿名报警
Next door thought they heard a pistol crack
隔壁的人觉得在昨晚九点左右
about nine o'clock last night.
听到了手枪声
That would chime with the grandfather.
这和老古董的说法相吻合
-Morning, gentlemen.  -Doctor.
-早上好 先生们  -法医
Oh, yes.
噢 是的
That does look nasty.
看起来挺糟糕
You seem to be making a habit of collecting these, Chief Inspector.
看来你是要集齐这一类的案件了 总督察
Shot?
枪杀
In the back of the head at point-blank range
近距离击中后脑勺
would be my first impression.
我的第一判断
Three in as many days.
这几天的第三起了
Oh...
噢
And I think his wife has just arrived by taxi.
我想他的夫人应该刚下出租车
Good heavens, it's...
天呐 这是
Detective Sergeant Strange, Mrs Maynard.
我是Strange警长 Maynard太太
If we could speak inside.
我们能去里面聊聊吗
-Where have you come from?  -The station.
-你从哪里开过来的  -车站
I picked her up from here and dropped her there last night.
我昨晚从这里接的她 然后把她送到那儿的
-What time was this?  -Er, 5:45.
-是在什么时间  -呃 5点45
Something like that.
大概是这个时候
She'd booked a return for 9:30 this morning.
她预约了一个今天早上九点半的返程
Look, can I go now? I've got a pick up in Headington.
那么 我能走了吗 我还得去Headington接客
Brian's not turned in and Ifan's doing his nut.
Brian还没有回来 Ifan也没有空
No, I'd like you to give this officer a formal statement
不行 我需要你向这位警官做一个陈述
and then you can leave.
然后才可以走
Go on.
去吧
Are you OK?
还好吗
-Three shootings in a week?  -Shh...
-一周内的第三起枪杀案  -嘘
-Here...  -What's this?
-给  -这是什么
It's your Ostrich Fanciers' Club.
这是你的鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部
One of the classified ads boys recognised the name.
一个负责广告分类的男孩认出了这个名字
"The glamour of exotic rare birds."
"异域珍禽的魅力所在"
"Films £1.
"胶片1镑
"Send a stamped address envelope to The Ostrich Fanciers' Club,
"信封需贴2.5便士邮票 寄至 鸵鸟同好俱乐部
"The Rectory, 12 Cloister Walk, Oxon."
"教区长宅邸 修道院步行街12号 牛津郡"
Exotic rare birds?
异域珍禽
For the one-in-the-hand brigade, I fancy,
我猜 是有些组织宁愿"一鸟在手"
rather than the two-in-the-bush contingent.
也不愿放任"二鸟在林"
Right.
是了
Happy to be of personal service.
很高兴能帮到你
Thank you.
谢了
We understand he was involved in the Masonic Order.
我们得知他是共济会的一员
Is that right?
是这样吗
He was in charge of the lodge.
他在会所里管事
We only had our ladies' night this week.
我们这周只去了那次女士晚宴
He was so proud.
他很以此为傲
Mrs Maynard...
Maynard太太
..does The Ostrich Fanciers' Club mean anything to you?
鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部对你意味着什么吗
No.
不
Nothing at all. Should it?
并没有 该有吗
Oh, now, that's a shame.
噢 真是可惜了
The clock's broken, sir.
这个钟坏了 长官
And it always kept such good time.
它一直都很准时
Harry wouldn't have had it in the house otherwise.
不然Harry也不会一直把它放在家里
Sir...
长官
There are two indentations in the flower bed,
花坛里有两个压痕
spaced about a foot apart.
间隔约一英尺
I think I know who made the tip-off call.
我想我知道是谁匿名报警的了
A ladder, you mean?
你是指 那个梯工
Well, if Acacia Avenue is on Lee Timothy's round,
如果Acacia大道就在Lee Timothy的附近
I can understand why he wouldn't want to be found
我可以理解为什么他不想在
at the scene of a murder two days running.
连续两天的谋杀案现场被发现
What's all that about Maynards carriage clock?
Maynard家的旅行钟是怎么回事
Changing the time seems to be the killer's calling card.
更改时间似乎是这个凶手的特色
Though, God knows why.
大概只有上帝知道吧
-What do you think, Morse?  -I've...
-你怎么看 Morse  -我之前
-I've seen this room before.  -What, been here, you mean?
-我之前见过这个房间  -什么 你是指 你来过这儿
This is the room where Dudley Lunn's blue film was shot.
这间房间就是Dudley Lunn拍色情片的地方
But you can see why I didn't want to get involved.
但你明白我为什么不想掺合进来
Two people dead on the round
两天内有两个人死在了附近
in two days could play havoc on my goodwill.
我的好意或许会给自己带来麻烦
I'm Squeegee Lee, not Typhoid Mary!
我只是玻璃Lee 不是风暴Mary
-How well did you know the Maynards?  -They're customers.
-你和Maynard一家熟吗  -就是普通客户
I clean the windows, they pay me. That's it.
我清理窗户 他们付钱 就是这样
And where were you last night at nine o'clock?
那你昨晚九点的时候在哪里
Meeting my bird, wasn't I?
见我女朋友 不行吗
She works of an evening part-time.
她晚上有兼职
Gets off about 10:00 and I walk her home.
10点左右结束 我陪她走回家
So, no-one can vouch for your movements last night at 9:00?
所以 没有人可以证明你昨晚九点的行踪了
Not when you put it like that. No.
如果你这么说的话 没有
Right.
好的
Morse.
Morse
Ah, Morse.
啊 Morse
I was hoping for a few words with DCI Thursday.
我想和Thursday总督察说几句话
He's gone to London, sir.
他去伦敦了 长官
Looking for a lead on this Ostrich Fanciers' Club.
去找鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部的领头人
We think Father Mahoney's step-brother,
我们觉得Mahoney神父的弟弟
Donal, might be involved.
Donal 可能和案子有关
This smutty films case, wretched business.
这些低俗的影片 肮脏的交易
Very well. Keep me apprised of any developments.
很好 有什么进展随时向我汇报
-Carry on.  -Sir.
-去吧  -是
Ah, matey, glad I caught you.
啊 伙计 正好遇上你
I've got this woman being knocked about by her husband.
有一位女士正受到丈夫的家暴
Uniform would like us to take a statement.
同事们想让我们去录口供
Can you deal?
你能来吗
Well, it's that or watching DeBryn
要不然你就看着DeBryn
rooting around Maynard's brain pan at the postmortem.
在验尸房翻查Maynard的头盖骨
I thought you'd sooner the frail.
你还不如选那位太太
I won't press charges.
我不会起诉的
It's my fault. I provoked him.
都是我的错 我惹恼了他
There's nothing you could have done that would warrant this.
无论你做了什么 他也不该这样对你
I met somebody.
我认识了别人
I went with him.
跟他交往了
And your husband found out?
被你丈夫发现了
And who was he, this other man?
那个男人是谁
-I don't want him getting in any trouble.  -Please, Mrs Grady.
-我不想让他惹上麻烦  -请说出来吧 Grady太太
It's Dudley.
是Dudley
Dudley Lunn.
Dudley Lunn
Where can I find your husband?
你丈夫现在在哪
He's at a place called Paradise Court.
他在一个叫天堂院的地方
But I don't want to press any charges.
但我不想起诉
Mrs Grady?
Grady太太
Joan Thursday, Welfare Officer.
我是Joan Thursday 社工
You don't have to talk to Detective Sergeant Morse if you don't want to.
你不想说的话可以不跟Morse探长说
I've told him I don't want to press charges.
我跟他说了我不想起诉
Please...
拜托了
Well, then, that should be enough.
好的 说这些就够了
Thank you, Officer.
谢谢 警官
Well, if you change your mind, you can find me at Castle Gate.
如果你改主意了 可以来城门警局找我
-Are you sure about Grady?  -I'm not sure, no.
-你确定是Grady吗  -我不确定
But it's a bit of a coincidence that his wife's lover
但他妻子的情夫在他工作地附近的乡间小道上
is killed on a country lane not far from where he works.
被杀害了 这也太巧了吧
Good evening. We're looking for your groundsman, Del Grady.
晚上好 我们在找你们的园丁 Del Grady
We've tried his home, to no avail.
我们去他家找过 但没找到
Some sort of Peeping Tom?
是偷窥狂吗
A groundsman at a naturist camp,
在天体营做园丁
it's hard to imagine a position
这种职位
that affords greater opportunity for voyeurism.
对于偷窥狂来说简直就是天时地利
Anything out of the ordinary, Doc?
有什么反常之处吗 法医
All too ordinary, I'm afraid.
恐怕是太正常了
The postmortem may say otherwise.
验尸结果也许会有反转
But at first glance,
但乍看之下
there's nothing to say it's other than it looks.
跟表面现象没什么相反之处
-Suicide.  -For the Coroner to decide, of course.
-自杀  -当然还需要验尸官确认
But there's a strong smell of liquor about the corpus.
不过尸体上有强烈的酒气
Alcohol taken to excess is a notorious depressant,
众所周知 过量饮酒会让人消沉
and we rarely make wise choices when inebriated.
喝醉的时候很难做出明智的选择
Anyway, er, shall we say nine of the clock?
晚上九点见吧
Mm-hm. Doctor.
好的 法医
Morse.
Morse
So...
所以
..he puts his wife in hospital...
他把妻子打进了医院
..then does for himself in a fit of remorse, then?
然后出于悔恨自杀了
Or it's what he did to Lunn
或者是他对Lunn等人
and the others that just pushed him over the edge.
犯下的罪行让他走上了极端
I can see Lunn,
看得出来他为什么杀Lunn
if he was carrying on with Mrs Grady.
如果他和Grady太太有染
But where's your motive for Father Mahoney and Commodore Maynard?
但是杀害Mahoney神父和Maynard准将的动机呢
They can't have been seeing her, too.
他们不可能也在和她交往
I'll get on for a search warrant.
我会去申请搜查令
But unless Grady has a .22 pistol at home,
但是除非Grady家里放着一把22口径手枪
we're gonna have to look elsewhere for a killer.
不然凶手就要从别处查起了
It was just a mistake.
只是个错误
A silly, youthful indiscretion.
年轻时傻傻的冲动
Did you meet him...
那天晚上
..the other night, down by the lane?
你在小路那边和他见面了吗
Only, my colleague found a paper flower
我同事在Lunn的出租车停靠的地方
out by where Lunn's taxi was parked.
发现了一片纸花
And I know that you and your wife
我知道你和你妻子
were given Hawaiian garlands the evening you arrived.
到这里的那天晚上收到了夏威夷花环
I just wanted to clear the air.
我只是想和他说清楚
To make plain that whatever youthful indiscretion had taken place
无论年轻时我们有过什么样的冲动
belonged in the past.
那都是过去式了
I'm a married man now.
我已经结婚了
-And so was Del.  -Well, he was.
-Del也是  -确实结过
But far less happy than you.
但远没有你那么幸福
How did he take that?
他是怎么想的
Not well.
不太能接受
He was trapped in a marriage with someone he didn't care for.
他跟不爱的人结了婚 困在婚姻里
He'd only gone through with it because it was expected of him,
他只能默默忍受 因为背负着这样的期待
and to please his family.
也为了让家人开心
So, that's where you were when you heard the gunshot.
所以听见枪声的时候你就在那里
And rather than having to answer any awkward questions
你们不愿意去回答那些令人尴尬的问题
about what you both were doing there,
你们俩在那里干嘛
you agreed to keep quiet about it.
于是决定保持沉默
Del begged me to meet him in town
Del求我第二天晚上和他见面
the following evening to finish our talk.
好继续我们的谈话
I'm afraid I left him with no illusions.
但我没给他留下任何幻想
Or hope.
或者希望
Does Mrs Appleby know about your, erm...
Appleby太太知道你们
.. "youthful indiscretion"?
年轻时的冲动吗
No, of course not.
当然不知道
Right, well, thank you.
好吧 谢谢你
We'll be in touch if we need any more information.
如果需要更多信息我们会联系你
I'm after Dinner For Three.
我要找《三人晚餐》
Outside, all of you!
出去 全都出去
I know you've been a long time out of the Smoke, Fred,
我知道你离开伦敦很久了 Fred
but it's still manners to pay your respects
但还是要讲点礼貌
when you come on somebody else's patch.
来到别人的地盘要拜拜码头吧
-I didn't like to bother you, Len.  -It's no bother.
-我不想麻烦你 Len  -不麻烦
And it's Commander Dury these days. Oh...
现在要叫我Dury长官了
For what it's worth.
就是这样
You've been talking to Ches Finch.
你找Ches Finch聊过了
Well, we were probationers together.
我们以前一起做过保释官
At Cable Street.
在Cable警局
The Dirty Squad falls under my eye these days.
扫黄组现在归我管了
-What's your interest?  -A murder with a link to blue films
-你想干嘛  -有桩谋杀案与色情电影有关
sold by a firm called The Ostrich Fanciers' Club.
是一家叫鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部的公司发售的
How it is, Fred.
这样吧 Fred
We've got it just how the upstairs like it.
我们保证让上级刚好满意
Nice and quiet, no trouble.
安静稳当 不作妖
Sure.
好
DI Nesbitt and DS Sneed will put the word out.
Nesbitt探员和Sneed探长会把话放出去
If it's some interloper, you can have them.
如果真的有人搞事 就交给你
If not...?
如果没有
Tell them they're looking for a shitehawk
告诉他们 要找的这个混蛋
in a trilby with an orange feather. About your size.
戴着橙色羽毛装饰的呢帽 跟你身材差不多
When did you blackmail Mahoney?
你什么时候敲诈Mahoney的
When he was prison chaplain at Wandsworth?
他在Wandsworth当监狱牧师的时候吗
What do you have on him? Boys, was it?
你有他什么把柄 恋童是吗
The flesh is weak.
人是软弱的
So, you put the squeeze on,
所以你向他施压
he fronts up your racket beyond the Smoke.
让他负责你在伦敦之外的那些勾当
From time to time, you drop by, posing as his half-brother Donal,
你假装他的继兄弟Donal 时不时去找他
to keep an eye on proceedings.
盯着他的行动
Is there a real Donal?
真的有Donal这个人吗
Or was that just for someone who might ask questions?
还是说只是编出来应付别人的好奇心
Like his housekeeper, for instance.
比如说他的管家
I could hardly show her my warrant card, could I?
我又不能给她看我的警官证 是吧
What happened, Len?
发生了什么 Len
You were a good thief-taker once.
你以前是坏蛋克星
We're none of us as clean as we'd like the world to think, eh?
我们倒希望世人看我们是清白的 但谁有那么清白呢
Well...
好吧
..the priest is dead now, whoever did for him.
不管是谁干的 牧师已经死了
The way I read it, I've got three men dead...
在我看来 现在有三个人死了
..all connected to your little caper.
全都跟你的非法勾当有关
Maybe someone's decided to put you out of business.
也许是有人想把你踢出这一行
I'll be seeing you.
回头见
Fred...
Fred
Your card's marked.
你已经被盯上了
For old times.
看在老交情的份上
Don't come back.
别再来了
What you do in your sewer is your concern.
你在这下三滥的地方干什么是你的事
You can be king of the shit heap for all it means to me.
在我看来 你在下水沟里称王称霸都随便
But you set foot on my ground again...
但你要是再踏上我的地盘
..you'll all swing.
你们死定了
I don't care whose coat you're carrying.
我不管你上头有什么人
-Ah, Morse.  -Sir.
-Morse  -长官
-Developments?  -Some, sir.
-有进展吗  -有一些 长官
I think we can rule out the passenger
我们应该可以排除
that Lunn picked up at the station.
Lunn在车站接到的那个乘客
How so? Oh, may I offer you...?
怎么说 要来一杯
Yes, sir. Whisky, if I may.
好的 长官 威士忌 谢谢
-What's this?  -What?
-这是什么  -什么
Oh, well, it's just a... Just a hobby.
哦 这个啊 只是个爱好
-These are very good, sir.  -Oh, thank you.
-画得特别好 长官  -谢谢
Clearing out my wife's clothes,
清理我妻子的衣服的时候
I found my old watercolour box at the back of the wardrobe.
我在衣柜后面找到了以前的水彩盒
You were saying?
你刚刚说什么
Oh, yes, she appears to have been his mistress.
哦对 她好像是他的情妇
He dropped her at home at 9:20 to a beating from her husband.
他9点20把她送回到家 然后她被丈夫打了
Who is she?
她是谁
Oh, yes, Miss Parry.
是Parry小姐
Life model at the art school.
美术学校里的绘画模特
Yes, she's quite striking, isn't she?
她很美 是吧
Cheers.
干杯
Miss Parry?
Parry小姐
Yes.
对
And what time would that have been?
那是什么时候
Oh, I finished about nine o'clock.
我是九点左右结束的
Ah, good morning, sir.
早上好 长官
Sir, do you remember Mr Roberts, the dispatcher from Speedy Cabs?
长官 你记得Roberts先生吗 极速出租车的调度员
He's very kindly offered to come in
今天早上他过来
and help us out with a statement this morning.
帮我们录一份口供
-A statement?  -Just a small matter concerning timings.
-口供  -就问点时间上的事
Mr Roberts, can you tell us what time
Roberts先生 你让Joe North去
did you give Joe North the job to pick up Mrs Maynard from her house?
Maynard太太家接她是几点
Mid-afternoon. 3:30, four o'clock.
下午三点多 三点半 四点的样子
Right. And was that over the telephone or...?
是打的电话还是
No, he popped into the office.
不是 他去了趟办公室
Most of the fellas do around that time, you know, if they're slack.
那个时间 小伙子们没什么事的话都会过去
And Speedy Cabs, they sponsor a table
极速出租车为Maynard准将举办的
at Commodore Maynard's lodge charity nights.
共济会地方分会慈善晚宴提供赞助
-Is that right?  -Oh, yes.
-是吗  -是的
Now, would Joe North have ever gone to those events?
Joe North参加过这种活动吗
Oh, we've all been to one or two of those.
我们都去过一两次啊
Joe included.
Joe也一样
You don't think he's involved, do you? Not Joe!
你不会觉得是他吧 Joe不可能的
Why, I can't believe it.
我不信
Sir, do you remember that we found Commodore Maynard's body
长官 您还记不记得 我们是在一个落地摆钟前发现的
in front of the grandfather clock?
Maynard准将的尸体
The key was on the floor next to him.
钥匙在他身旁的地板上
-The glass door was open so he could wind it.  -Exactly.
-玻璃门开着 是为了给钟上发条  -没错
His wife told us he always wound the clocks at 9:00.
他妻子说他一般会在9点给钟上发条
-Right.  -So, we've been lucky,
-对  -那我们就很幸运了
insofar as we've been able to establish
可以确定这几个谋杀案
at what time each of the murders took place.
发生的时间
Dudley Lunn just before 10:00.
Dudley Lunn差不多是10点
Father Mahoney at 8:00.
Mahoney神父是八点
And Commodore Maynard at 9:00.
Maynard准将是9点
Which tells us...
这就说明
..that the killer changed the time on a watch or clock
在每一个犯罪现场 凶手都调整了
at each of the scene of crimes.
手表或者时钟的时间
So, at ten o'clock,
他把Dudley Lunn的
he changed Dudley Lunn's watch to 6:50.
手表从10点调成6点50分
At eight o'clock, he changed Father Mahoney's pocket watch to 3:50.
把Mahoney神父的怀表从8点调成3点50分
And at nine o'clock,
把Maynard准将的
he changed Commodore Maynard's carriage clock to 3:10.
马车钟从9点调成3点10分
Now, we thought that he was trying to just supply himself
我们之前以为他是想给自己制造假的不在场证明
with a false alibi. But it's actually far, far simpler than that.
但其实没那么复杂
If you say so.
愿闻其详
The actual time is immaterial.
时间是几点并不重要
It's the position of the hands on the clock that's important.
重要的是时针分针的位置
To use the terminology that was drilled into us in Signals.
用我们学的信号术语来说
6:50, left hand down, right hand high.
6点50分 左手下垂 右手在右上方
3:50, left hand out, right hand high.
3点50分 左手平举 右手在右上方
3:10, left hand out, right hand across high.
3点10分 左手平举 右手过头顶在左上方
-Semaphore?  -Exactly.
-旗语  -没错
Mine's a bit rusty, but C-Y-W?
我有点忘了 是C Y W吗
C-Y-W, yes.
对 C Y W
It doesn't mean anything.
没什么含义啊
No, well, it's a puzzle, isn't it?
不太能理解 是吧
Ah, Miss Parry.
啊 Parry小姐
Fy nghyw bach!
Fy nghyw bach
Oh...!
噢
Cyw...
Cyw
Thank you, Miss Parry, for coming in
Parry小姐 感谢你过来
to confirm what you confided in me earlier.
证实了之前跟我说过的话
Constable, if you can escort her to the canteen,
警员 麻烦带她去食堂那边
I'll see you in a moment.
我一会就过去
Yes, of course, sir, you're right. C-Y-W doesn't mean anything.
长官 您说得没错 CYW在英语里
In English.
是没什么含义
But in Welsh...
但在威尔士语里
..and perhaps you can help me with my pronunciation here,
我要是发音不对 你可以纠正我
cyw is a term of endearment.
cyw是一种爱称
It means "chick".
意为宝贝
Now, you said to us...
你之前跟我们说
.."This is Siwan.
这是Siwan
"Joan, she'd be in English.
英语里是Joan
"But most people call her Birdie." Yes?
但很多人都叫她小黄莺 对吧
So she was to everyone else.
别人是这么叫她
But to me...
但对我来说
..fy nghyw bach.
fy nghyw bach
My little chick.
她就是我的小宝贝
Cyw.
Cyw
I recognised her
长官 我看到
from Superintendent Bright's sketchpad, sir.
Bright警司的画板才认出了她
Although she now calls herself Lynn Parry,
虽然她现在随了她母亲的姓
after her mother's maiden name.
自称为Lynn Parry
She's also the blonde in the blue films made with Dudley Lunn.
但她就是那个和Dudley Lunn一起拍色情片的金发女郎
Ifan Roberts, I'm arresting you for the murder of Dudley Lunn,
Ifan Roberts 你因谋杀Dudley Lunn
Father Mahoney and Commodore Maynard.
Mahoney神父和Maynard准将被逮捕了
Presumably you watched Lunn for a long time.
你应该盯了Lunn很长时间吧
Planning, waiting for your moment.
然后伺机而动
You knew he was knocking off Patty Grady.
你知道他和Patty Grady有一腿
And you knew that Mr Grady worked at Paradise Court.
也知道Grady先生在天堂院上班
I watched them all for a month, on and off.
他们几个我断断续续盯了一个月
Nobody notices taxis.
没人会注意出租车
Get behind the wheel of a cab and you might as well be invisible.
开出租还是降低存在感的好
But we see everything.
但我们什么都知道
The pathetic secrets.
可悲的小秘密
The carrying on.
令人不齿的勾当
All of it.
全都知道
As a dispatcher, you were perfectly placed
你作为调度员 给Lunn派个假活
to send Lunn on a non-existent job to Hovelle Wood,
让他去Hovelle树林 并不是什么难事
where you would be waiting for him.
然后你就在那等着他
Ifan, what's...?
Ifan 你
What's this about?
你这是要干什么
See what you did, Dudley, to my Siwan!
Dudley 看看你对我的Siwan都干了些什么
-Eh? Tell me who else is involved!  -No-one.
-告诉我还有谁  -没别人了
Tell me!
说
You probably told him he'd live if he gave you what you wanted.
你告诉他 说出名字就饶他一命
How did you discover your daughter was involved?
你怎么发现你女儿牵涉其中的
Oh...
噢
I see. Of course.
我知道了
You'd become a member of The Ostrich Fanciers' Club.
你是鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部的会员
You'd ordered some of their films.
你买了他们的片子
You saw her.
然后看到了她
I knew her at once.
我一眼就认出了她
She was my little girl.
她是我的女儿
Fy nghyw bach!
我的小宝贝
He was just a name on a card twice a year.
他对我来说不过是卡片上的名字 一年见两次
"Love, Dad."
爱你的爸爸
Dad? What does that even mean?
爸爸 这到底意味着什么呢
I barely remember him.
我对他都没什么印象
Perhaps. But he never forgot you.
也许吧 但他从未忘记过你
Well, maybe it would have been better for everyone if he had.
说不定他忘了对大家都好
Something far easier said than done for any father.
对每个父亲来说 有些事是说起来容易做起来难
What can you think of me?
你会怎么看我
I think you're an intelligent, sensitive, young woman
我觉得你年轻 聪明 体贴
who fell amongst scoundrels.
只是没遇上好人
Any shame is on their side.
该羞愧的是他们
Not yours.
不是你
Thank you.
谢谢你
45, 45, pick up
45号 45号 新订单
98B Chestnut Way, New Hinkley.
从新辛克利栗树路98B号
Going to...
到
..North Oxford Lawn Tennis Club.
北牛津草场网球俱乐部
Passenger's a Miss Carlitt.
乘客是Carlitt小姐
Yeah, Roger, Clarry. On way.
收到 Clarry 我出发了
I should've tumbled.
我早该想到的
Crossed flags on his arm.
他手臂上纹的交叉旗
It's the badge of a Naval signalman.
是海军信号员的标志
And what of the graffiti?
那墙上的字呢
Micah.5.15.
弥迦书第五章第十五节
"And I will execute vengeance with anger and fury upon the heathen
我必在盛怒之下 向那不听从的
"such as they have not heard."
异教徒施报
He did it in her name. I can't say I blame him.
他是为了她才这么做的 也不能怪他
-If it had been my daughter...  -Ah, but it never would be.
-要是我女儿的话  -那不可能
It could happen to anyone.
发生在谁身上都有可能
Given the right circumstances.
如果是在特定的情形下
They're all somebody's daughter.
她们会是别人的女儿
Somebody's mother, sister.
母亲 姐妹
They all mean something to someone.
有人会在乎她们
Or did once.
或者说在乎过她们
And now because of The Ostrich Fanciers' Club,
现在因为鸵鸟爱好者俱乐部
they mean nothing to anyone.
没人在乎她们了
Except to us.
除了我们
They mean something to us.
我们在乎她们
To me, at least.
至少我是如此
I'd have said to you, too, once.
以前我也跟你说过
Well, I'm not the fool I was.
我不像以前那么蠢了
I quite liked that fool.
我还挺喜欢以前的你
He hoped for the best in people.
愿意把人往好处想
Surely, it's better to see things as they are.
还是实事求是点好
People make bad choices, they have to pay the consequences.
人们做错了选择 就要承担后果
What about pity, understanding?
那同情 理解呢
Where does that fit into the picture?
都不考虑吗
I'm not here to...
我该做的事
..kiss the wounded.
不是抚慰伤痛
I'm here to make sure justice gets done.
伸张正义才是我的职责所在
The rest I can leave to the likes of Father Mahoney,
其余的就交给Mahoney神父那样的人吧
for all the good it did him.
虽然他也没落得什么好下场
Well...
那
..I'm sure you know best.
你自己想清楚就行
Another beer? Or are you bitter enough?
再来一杯 还是就此打住
No, I won't. I've got something on tonight.
不喝了 我晚上还有事
We're who we are, Morse.
人的本性是不会改变的 Morse
Our nature...
再怎么逃离
..we can try to escape it.
我们最终还是会
But it'll find us out in the end.
回归本性
A man's what he is.
不论是否愿意
Whether he likes it or not.
你就是你